now let's see another type of predictor
that combines prediction decisions which
is called a hierarchical predictor it is
similar to a tournament predictor but
the tournament predictor typically is
trying to combine two good predictors
one is better for some branches the
other for others a hierarchical
predictor is trying to combine a good
predictor with an okay predictor here
you're basically doing two good
predictions for every Branch just to use
one of them and each of the good
predictors costs you a lot for each
entry here the idea is that you have a
very good predictor that costs you a lot
for its entry but you don't want to be
using the good predictor for branches
that are very easy to predict anyway so
the idea is that for those branches you
want to use the okay predictor and use
the good predictor entries which are
very expensive only for branches that
really need that good predictor so in
the tournament predictor you will update
both predictors on each decision so that
they can both stay current with what's
going on and thus they both try to do
their best on each branch decision but
in the hierarchical predictor you might
update the okay predictor on each
decision but you update the good
predictor only if the okay predictor did
not work well for that Branch the idea
here is to not use the entries of the
good predictor if the okay one is doing
fine on this Branch so really what that
means is that we can have very expensive
entries in the good predictor and we
have relatively few entries because most
of the branches will be handled just
fine with the okay predictor if we try
to compare the tournament predictor with
the hierarchical predictor the
hierarchical one usually wins because it
turns out that there are many many
branches that can be predicted just fine
using something like just a simple 2bit
counter on the other hand there are some
branches that really require a very
strong predictor to predict them in a
tournament predictor each of the
predictors is a balance between cost and
accuracy in this predictor you can build
a very expensive predictor with very few
entries and an okay predictor that has a
lot of Entry so most branches get
handled by this which leaves the rest of
the resources for the good predictor and
that means that it can have extremely
long histories or be a very very fancy
predictor you can even have a hierarchy
or for that matter a tournament with
more than just two predictors